Guide to the Josiah William Bailey Papers, 1833-1967, bulk 1900-1946 RL.00065
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Senatorial Series, 1930-1946, 436 boxes
  - Housing Subseries, 1931-1946
    Correspondence, telegrams, and printed material relate to matters affecting housing. The bulk of the material during the early 1930's concerns efforts by the Federal government to help homeowners pay mortgages and refinance their houses through the Home Loan Bill, the National Housing Act, and the Home Owners Loan Corporation (HOLC). The problems of building and loan associations were also discussed. Much of the correspondence is routine, either constituent mail expressing opinion on various bills or individual requests for assistance in obtaining loans. Included is a pamphlet (1935) put out by the Federal Housing Authority (FHA) entitled Modernization for Profit showing businessmen and homeowners how to redesign old buildings for modern use. Papers for the late 1930s generally relate to the FHA and its policies, expecially in North Carolina; slum clearance; and low income housing projects. During the war years, material concerns defense housing, housing shortages, rent control, and several bills to liquidate HOLC. Material is arranged chronologically by month.
    - Housing, 1930- 1934, April (Box 504)
    - Housing, 1934, May-Dec. (Box 505)
    - Housing, 1935, Jan.-Oct. (Box 506)
    - Housing, 1935, Nov.-1937, June (Box 507)
    - Housing, 1937, July-1939, Feb. (Box 508)
    - Housing, 1939, March-1940, June (Box 509)
    - Housing, 1940, July-1943, March (Box 510)
    - Housing, 1943, April-1946, March (Box 511)
    - Housing, 1946, April-Dec. (Box 512)
  - Relief Subseries, 1931-1946
    Correspondence, telegrams, petitions, statements, and printed material pertain to efforts of the U. S. government to provide various forms of relief for its citizens. The material is concentrated during the years of the Depression of the early 1930s. Much of the correspondence is devoted to the passage of an Old Age Pension Bill, various relief bills, the Social Security Bill, and appropriations for governmental relief agencies, especially the Civilian Conservation Corps (CCC), the Public Works Administration (PWA), and the Civil Works Administration (CWA). There is also considerable information dealing with specific North Carolina relief projects funded by the CCC, the PWA, and the CWA. During the late 1930's and the 1940's, correspondence related principally to continuation of relief appropriations, funding of specific projects, and amendments to the Social Security Act. Material is arranged chronologically by month.
    1932: Costigan-LaFollette Act providing relief for the unemployed; bill for the relief of widows and dependents of Spanish-American War veterans; Old Age Pensions; Emergency Officer's Retirement Bill.
    1933: Old Age Pensions; Relief Bill; National Recovery Administration codes.
    1934: Old Age Pensions.
    1935: Old Age Pensions; Social Security; unemployment insurance.
    1936: Funding for PWA projects.
    1937: Continued relief appropriations.
    1939: Continuation of various relief measures; Social Security
    1940: Continuation of WPA and PWA expenditures; Social Security.
    1945-1946: Social Security Act amendments.
    - Relief, 1930-1932, March (Box 513)
    - Relief, 1932, March-1933, March (Box 514)
    - Relief, 1933, April-1934, Jan. (Box 515)
    - Relief, 1934, Jan.-March (Box 516)
    - Relief, 1934, March-June (Box 517)
    - Relief, 1934, June-1935, Feb. (Box 518)
    - Relief, 1935, Feb.-March (Box 519)
    - Relief, 1935, April-June (Box 520)
    - Relief, 1935, June-Oct. (Box 521)
    - Relief, 1935, Oct.-1936, Feb. (Box 522)
    - Relief, 1936, Feb.-June (Box 523)
    - Relief, 1936, June-Dec. (Box 524)
    - Relief, 1936, Dec.-1937, May (Box 525)
    - Relief, 1937, May-Dec. (Box 526)
    - Relief, 1938, Jan.-May (Box 527)
    - Relief, 1938, May-1939, Jan. (Box 528)
    - Relief, 1939, Jan.-June (Box 529)
    - Relief, 1939, June-Dec. (Box 530)
    - Relief, 1939, Dec.-1940, April (Box 531)
    - Relief, 1940, April-1941, Feb. (Box 532)
    - Relief, 1941, March-1942, Feb. (Box 533)
    - Relief, 1942, Feb.-1943, March (Box 534)
    - Relief, 1943, March-1944 (Box 535)
    - Relief, 1945-1946, undated (Box 536)
  - Reorganization of the Government Subseries, 1937-1938
    Correspondence and telegrams contain constituent opinion on Roosevelt's proposed Executive Reorganization Bill. While the bulk of the replies from Bailey's office were routine, there are some lengthy letters from Bailey concerning his views on this bill. Material is arranged chronologically by day.
    - Reorganization of the Government, 1937-1938 (Box 537)
  - Tennessee Valley Authority Subseries, 1931-1946
    Correspondence and printed material are related to the Tennessee Valley Authority (TVA), various flood control and electric projects associated with TVA, and funding for these projects. There is material concerning Muscle Shoals, dams across the French Broad and the Hiawassee rivers, the Cherokee Dam, flood control, an investigation of TVA (1937), the Bone Bill (1941-1942), and the McKellar Amendment to abolish revolving funds (1946). Material is arranged chronologically by month.
    - Tennessee Valley Authority, 1931-1938 (Box 538)
    - Tennessee Valley Authority, 1938-1946 (Box 539)